<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Daniel Standage</title><link href="https://standage.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://standage.github.io/feeds/roundup.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://standage.github.io/</id><updated>2016-02-26T10:30:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Reading roundup</title><link href="https://standage.github.io/reading-roundup-2016-02-26.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-02-26T10:30:00-05:00</published><author><name>Daniel S. Standage</name></author><id>tag:standage.github.io,2016-02-26:reading-roundup-2016-02-26.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://genome.fieldofscience.com/2016/01/nejm-editorial-calls-data-scientists.html"&gt;This commentary I missed previously on the "research parasites" fiasco&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disproving a claim using the same data is what reproducibility is all about, and this is one of the most important reasons that data needs to be shared.
After all, if someone has distorted their data in order to reach a conclusion that isn't really justified, we need someone else–someone not invested in proving the same result–to re-analyze the data using independent methods.
This is how science corrects itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://opencontent.org/blog/archives/4443"&gt;This post on open educational resources (OER)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anderson goes on to critique OER:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A big issue for the open source movement has been its sustainability.
And that’s one of the reasons you’re seeing a lot of legislation about it because they are looking basically to the taxpayer,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to hear more of this criticism of OER from publishers and AAP in the future. Why?
The US PIRG’s recent report &lt;a href="http://www.uspirg.org/reports/usp/covering-cost"&gt;Covering the Cost&lt;/a&gt; estimates that each year approximately $3B – that’s $3,000,000,000US – of financial aid dollars are spent by undergraduates on textbooks and other proprietary educational materials.
In other words, under the existing commercial textbook model students are simply valves through which taxpayer dollars flow to publishers.
I would love the opportunity to get this number in front of more people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://pyformat.info/"&gt;This HowTo on Python string formatting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python has had awesome string formatters for many years but the documentation on them is far too theoretic and technical.
With this site we try to show you the most common use-cases covered by the old and new style string formatting API with practical examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://simplystatistics.org/2016/02/16/when-it-comes-to-science-its-the-economy-stupid/"&gt;This post suggesting we fund science by lottery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m very confident in a peer review to detect the difference between psuedo-science and real science, or complete hype and realistic improvement.
But I’m much less confident in the ability of peer review to accurately distinguish “important” from “not important” research.
So I think we should consider seriously the lottery for these grants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each year all eligible scientists who meet some minimum entry requirements submit proposals for what they’d like to do scientifically.
Each year those proposals are reviewed to make sure they meet the very minimum bar (are they scientific? do they have relevant training at all?).
Among all the (very large) class of people who pass that bar we hold a lottery.
We take the number of research dollars and divide it up to give the maximum number of these grants possible.
These grants might be pretty small - just enough to fund the person’s salary and maybe one or two students/postdocs.
To make this works for labs that required equipment there would have to be cooperative arrangements between multiple independent indviduals to fund/sustain equipment they needed.
Renewal of these grants would happen as long as you were posting your code/data online, you were meeting peer review requirements, and responding to inquires about your work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;These posts on Sci-Hub and open access to research&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://blog.comicsgrid.com/2016/02/sci-hub-not-open-access/"&gt;This post&lt;/a&gt; claiming that Sci-Hub has brought much-needed attention to an important issue, but that it is not a long-term solution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://engineuring.wordpress.com/2016/02/24/why-sci-hub-is-the-true-solution-for-open-access-reply-to-criticism/"&gt;This response&lt;/a&gt; to the original post, from the Sci-Hub founder, which comes across as pretty reactionary and defensive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://bjoern.brembs.net/2016/02/sci-hub-as-necessary-effective-civil-disobedience/"&gt;This post&lt;/a&gt; which doesn't (ostensibly) take any sides on the debate, but describes Sci-Hub as necessary civil disobedience and (in my opinion) highlights the good from both previous arguments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;These threads on compiling GCC with OpenMP support on OS X.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was having trouble installing CD-HIT this week with Homebrew.
These two StackOverflow threads (&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/29109926/459780"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/23490170/459780"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) led me to the solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;brew reinstall gcc --without-multilib
brew install --build-from-source cd-hit
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="reproducibility"></category><category term="open"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="funding"></category><category term="homebrew"></category></entry><entry><title>Reading roundup</title><link href="https://standage.github.io/reading-roundup-2016-02-12.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-02-12T00:00:00-05:00</published><author><name>Daniel S. Standage</name></author><id>tag:standage.github.io,2016-02-12:reading-roundup-2016-02-12.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/nbt/journal/vaop/ncurrent/full/nbt.3442.html"&gt;This new paper on Sequence Bloom Trees for tractable search of huge RNA-Seq data sets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We use SBTs to search 2,652 human blood, breast and brain RNA-seq experiments for all 214,293 known transcripts in under 4 days using less than 239 MB of RAM and a single CPU.
Searching sequence archives at this scale and in this time frame is currently not possible using existing tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/p-e-w/maybe"&gt;This nifty Python package for vetting shell scripts before running them&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;maybe&lt;/strong&gt; allows you to run a command and see what it does to your files without actually doing it!
After reviewing the operations listed, you can then decide whether you really want these things to happen or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.1002333"&gt;This meta-analysis reporting the dismal state of reproducibility in biomedical literature&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emphasis mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this survey, we assessed the current status of reproducibility and transparency addressing these indicators in a random sample of 441 biomedical journal articles published in 2000–2014.
Only one study provided a full protocol &lt;strong&gt;and none made all raw data directly available&lt;/strong&gt;.
Replication studies were rare (n = 4), and only 16 studies had their data included in a subsequent systematic review or meta-analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1602.03031"&gt;This preprint suggesting the use of sequence alignment as the basis for a cryptocurrency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, since HTS read mapping requires substantial computational resources and fast analysis turnout is desired, Coinami uses the HTS read mapping as proof-of-work to generate valid blocks to main its own cryptocurrency system, which may help motivate volunteers to dedicate more resources.
The Coinami protocol includes mechanisms to ensure that jobs performed by volunteers are correct, and provides genomic data privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://mikethemadbiologist.com/2016/02/08/what-does-reproducibility-mean/"&gt;This blog post bemoaning the lack of nuance in the discussion of reproducibility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What bothers me about the reproducibility discussion is that, for the most part, we’re not discussing what reproducibility would and should mean, but rather it’s more along the lines of ALL TEH SCIENTISMZ ARE BROKEN!
Which makes for great pundity thinky-pieces, but doesn’t really help us do science within the real-world constraints that scientists experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="rnaseq"></category><category term="reproducibility"></category></entry><entry><title>Reading roundup</title><link href="https://standage.github.io/reading-roundup-2016-02-05.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-02-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><author><name>Daniel S. Standage</name></author><id>tag:standage.github.io,2016-02-05:reading-roundup-2016-02-05.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/climagic/status/694660103627259905"&gt;This tip for issuing an alarm when a site comes back up.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't have a &lt;code&gt;.wav/.mp3&lt;/code&gt; file handy, but a terminal bell (&lt;code&gt;\a&lt;/code&gt;) works just as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; ! curl -m &lt;span class="m"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt; http://www.example.com/&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;do&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; still down&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; sleep 30&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;done&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;$&amp;#39;\a\a\a&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.newyorker.com/tech/elements/do-the-new-big-money-science-prizes-work"&gt;This article about how big money science prizes are Doing It Wrong&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a larger problem is that these prizes are not an efficient use of funds.
Instead of funding science prizes, these billionaires should try funding the science itself.
Take particle physics—one of the main specialties in which Breakthrough Prizes have been awarded.
In that field, government funding has been cut back significantly, and budgets have been flat or declining for years.
The $27 million awarded by Yuri Milner, in 2012, would have funded perhaps two hundred and seventy new postdoctoral fellowships that year, or a smaller number of postdoctoral fellowships combined with endowed faculty positions.
That could more than double the current number of young researchers in the field.
With a larger group of young, talented, and ambitious scientists finding gainful employment, the likelihood of jumpstarting some new and exciting research would be significant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't agree with the idea to create tons more postdocs: the 2000s-era doubling of the NIH budget created a lot of Ph.D. studentships and postdoctoral fellowships but did not significantly change the landscape for permanent academic faculty and staff positions.
If you want to help the system, don't contribute to the attrition problem by funding more Ph.D.s or postdocs, mitigate it by creating more permanent career options for those already in the system!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/ncomms/2016/160202/ncomms10448/full/ncomms10448.html"&gt;This new paper in &lt;em&gt;Nature Comms&lt;/em&gt; reporting genetic profile of a "morning person"&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We conduct a genome-wide association analysis of self-reported morningness, followed by analyses of biological pathways and related phenotypes.
We identify 15 significantly associated loci, including seven near established circadian genes...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://mattgemmell.com/the-dao-of-the-shell/"&gt;This blog post on the "Dao of the shell"&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t take your fingers off the keyboard, because the mouse isn’t going to help you.
Everything is customisable and configurable… or you can equally just leave it alone.
The whole ethos of configuration on the shell is to set up an environment where you type less.
That’s a beautiful thing.
On a GUI, configuration is often just about giving you more stuff to drag a pointer over to, and then click upon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I agree with the sentiment: I spend a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of time in the shell, and it's as focusing and empowering as he describes.
But I think mutt is a horrible example to demonstrate this!
In my experience it's a huge pain to get working correctly, the documentation is sparse, and trying to piece together a sensible configuration from a dozen similar but slightly inconsistent neckbeard blog posts is not my idea of zen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/basic-science-can-t-survive-without-government-funding/"&gt;This piece arguing basic science's need for government funding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without government support, most basic scientific research will never happen.
This is most clearly true for the kind of pure research that has delivered enormous prestige and great intellectual benefits but no profits, such as the work that brought us the Higgs boson, or the understanding that a supermassive black hole sits at the center of the Milky Way, or the discovery of methane seas on the surface of Saturn's moon Titan.
Company research laboratories used to do this kind of work: experimental evidence for the big bang was discovered at AT&amp;amp;T's Bell Labs, resulting in a Nobel Prize.
Now those days are gone.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Even in applied fields, such as materials science and computer science, companies now understand that basic research is a form of charity—so they avoid it.
Scientists at Bell Labs created the transistor, but that invention earned billions for Intel (and Microsoft).
Engineers at Xerox PARC invented the modern graphical user interface, although Apple (and Microsoft) profited the most.
IBM researchers pioneered the use of giant magnetoresistance to boost hard-disk capacity but soon lost the disk-drive business to Seagate and Western Digital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not a convincing argument in my opinion.
I'm not saying I necessarily disagree with his opinion, I just don't think he does a good job of defending his claims.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="shell"></category><category term="funding"></category><category term="gwas"></category></entry><entry><title>Reading roundup</title><link href="https://standage.github.io/reading-roundup-2016-01-29.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-01-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><author><name>Daniel S. Standage</name></author><id>tag:standage.github.io,2016-01-29:reading-roundup-2016-01-29.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://phys.org/news/2016-01-brewer-yeast-hybridizes-wasp-gut.html"&gt;This commentary on wasps and the reproductive ecosystem of brewer's yeast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking the experiment a step further, the researchers found that the interbred strains tended to be more hardy inside the wasp gut then those that were not—over time, the pure breeds actually died off.
This, the researchers claim, proves that wasp gut reproduction is a major driver of yeast diversity in nature.
And , they add, that suggests that yeast are dependent on interaction with insects for evolutionary development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://bioconductor.org/packages/release/bioc/html/ComplexHeatmap.html"&gt;This R package for creating heatmaps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looks like a really useful tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://insidehpc.com/2016/01/sustainable-software-needs-a-change-in-the-culture-of-science/"&gt;This excellent piece on culture and sustainable software in science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Career paths in software engineering&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In academia in particular, this is a big challenge.
Faculty members, students, postdocs, and staff members may all be developing scientific software.
But, university employees, at all levels, who are interested in both science and software often feel compelled to leave academia due to the lack of recognition of their software activities and the lack of career paths that let them pursue their interests in a manner that they feel is sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.theallium.com/science-life/tears-of-joy-at-conference-as-bioinformaticist-says-i-wont-go-into-detail-of-algorithm/"&gt;This hilarious parody of biologists and algorithms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON DC – At a human genomics meeting today, there was widespread relief during the fourth talk of the day, when the bioinformaticist that was speaking told the audience “I am not going to go through the details of my algorithm”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Lots of commentary on the recent NEJM editorial on "research parasites"&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a small sampling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.opiniomics.org/the-age-of-the-dinosaurs-is-almost-over-nejm-publishes-one-of-their-last-dying-roars/"&gt;The age of the dinosaurs is almost over; NEJM publishes one of their last dying roars&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://mrandrewdwatt.com/from-our-cold-dead-hands-nejm-editorial-on-data-sharing/"&gt;From our cold dead hands: NEJM Editorial on Data Sharing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://benjiweber.co.uk/blog/2016/01/25/why-i-strive-to-be-a-0-1x-engineer/"&gt;This apt take on being a 0.1x engineer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trouble is, software has diseconomies of scale.
The more we build, the more expensive it becomes to build and maintain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.universityaffairs.ca/career-advice/from-phd-to-life/grad-school-is-part-of-your-career-too/"&gt;This reminder that graduate training is part of your career&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for those current students, I hope they can do as I didn’t.
When I was a student, I spent little time thinking about and planning for what would come after.
I was deeply unprepared for the world of paid employment.
I was unprepared psychologically to transition to non-academic work, but I was also unprepared for the practical aspects of career exploration and job searching.
I had never conducted an informational interview before.
I didn’t have a resume.
I had no idea that most applicants were networking their way to interviews, not simply applying cold.
And I was just as unprepared for the socio-cultural aspects of non-academic employment: working 9-5 in an office with colleagues who understood, implicitly, how one comports oneself as a professional in that environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="R"></category><category term="software"></category><category term="publishing"></category><category term="career"></category></entry><entry><title>Reading roundup</title><link href="https://standage.github.io/reading-roundup-2016-01-15.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-01-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><author><name>Daniel S. Standage</name></author><id>tag:standage.github.io,2016-01-15:reading-roundup-2016-01-15.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://sebastianraschka.com/Articles/2014_multiprocessing_intro.html"&gt;This great tutorial on multiprocessing in Python&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written as a Jupyter notebook nonetheless!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://chronicle.com/article/It-s-Just-a-Job-Right-/234794"&gt;This piece on academic "quit lit"&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were some good parts, but honestly I'm not sure what point this guy's trying to make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scholars want to pursue their research, unencumbered by headaches and heartache, and they want to communicate the results of their scholarship to the brightest and most interested students around.
Is that so much to ask?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes. It is.
At least if the person asking is an adult.
Before grad school, I worked for a talented screenwriter.
I watched her career get trod upon by Hollywood executives with stupid suggestions and even stupider commands.
Likewise, a friend’s father had his law career stifled by office politics and collegial jealousy.
The fact is that no profession is perfect.
Young architects dream of erecting museums but spend more time redesigning kitchens.
Even the "dream" professions are not immune: Aren’t movie stars always complaining about having to answer inane questions in pointless interviews?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The great irony is that so many of the academics who complain about the corporatization of universities run off to get corporate jobs, where all the problems these scholars link to corporatizing trends — one would presume — would be present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskiehl/Gooey"&gt;This Python module for slapping a GUI on any program&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gooey is attached to your code via a simple decorator on whichever method has your argparse declarations (usually &lt;code&gt;main&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;from gooey import Gooey

@Gooey      &amp;lt;--- all it takes! :)
def main():
    parser = ArgumentParser(...)
# rest of code
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://webdemo.myscript.com/#/demo/equation"&gt;This cool little web app that converts handwritten equations into LaTeX&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's pretty good as far as I can tell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://hopejahrensurecanwrite.com/2013/10/23/3-ways-to-be-an-ally/"&gt;This eye-opening piece on harrassment in academics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holy language warning, Batman!
Be prepared for a lot of f-bombs and other unsavory words...but then again she's shedding some much-needed light on an unsavory topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I learned from the internet is that nothing upsets my male colleagues more than the pernicious sexual harassment that has been happening right under their noses for years.
“What kind of world are we living in?” they wail, “And what can I do about it?”
Ever since I can remember, I’ve actually been a woman, and so maybe I can offer some constructive advice.
You can thank me later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.jide.com/en/remixos-for-pc"&gt;This splash page for Remix OS for desktop architectures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Built on the Android-x86 project, Remix OS for PC unlocks our next phase of development for Remix OS and introduces a whole new range of versatility to how and where you can Remix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Android on desktop?
Definitely something to watch.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="python"></category><category term="academics"></category></entry><entry><title>Reading roundup</title><link href="https://standage.github.io/reading-roundup-2016-01-08.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-01-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><author><name>Daniel S. Standage</name></author><id>tag:standage.github.io,2016-01-08:reading-roundup-2016-01-08.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.bloombergview.com/articles/2016-01-05/academic-publishing-is-all-about-status"&gt;This Bloomberg piece on academic publishing and the economics of status&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This trend will be familiar to anyone who has looked at admission rates to top universities.
Despite ever-rising tuition costs and the growth of much-cheaper online alternatives, the highest-status universities keep getting more selective.
The best way to understand this, I think, is to see both academic journals and top universities less as purveyors of information or knowledge than as dispensers of status.
Information may want to be free, but status will always be scarce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://ivory.idyll.org/blog/2016-sustaining-research-software-development.html"&gt;This blog post on sustaining research software&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Software is fast becoming a &lt;em&gt;sine qua non&lt;/em&gt; in research, and researchers and funding agencies have been trying with increasing urgency to figure out how to support sustainable software development.
There's a whole NSF program devoted to sustainable research software, and I think it's fair to say that one of the main subsurface goals of the BD2K program is to tackle the question of software (PSA: data isn't much use without software).
The USDA and bio bits of DOE are also running smack into the problem that the research programs they fund are utterly dependent on software, yet investments in software are often secondary and rarely yield software that is usable past the end of the grant.
It turns out that software development for research is a rather intransigent beast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://biorxiv.org/content/early/2015/11/16/031930.abstract"&gt;This preprint on the state of software in (evolutionary) biology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A topic that has received little attention in this context is the code quality of widely used codes.
Unfortunately, the majority of users tend to blindly trust software and the results it produces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://drhagen.com/blog/the-missing-11th-of-the-month/"&gt;This interesting analysis of references to dates and a suprising effect from OCR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So where did the rest of the missing 11th go?
Well, starting in the 1860s, the Google algorithm starts to make a rather peculiar error—it misreads 11th as nth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.theguardian.com/science/blog/2015/nov/26/why-combining-science-and-showmanship-risks-the-future-of-research"&gt;This Guardian article on showmanship in science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many years, medicine, dinosaurs, space travel, and human origins have all been highly visible and widely entertaining scientific topics.
And for many years, we have relied on evaluation by editorial and professional peer review in scientific journals, evaluative reporting by science journalists, and individual judgment of educated citizens to place new scientific claims into proper perspective.
?Under those conditions, the trend toward science showmanship was arguably tolerable because it usually rested on a foundation of solid science.
When it doesn’t, it becomes bad reality TV that pleases sponsors but shouldn’t be confused for knowledge about process or result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/matsen/37521f504a14aede644d"&gt;This gist describing "sane git diffs for Jupyter notebook"&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Jupyter notebooks are stored in JSON format, this converts them to Markdown for diffs you can actually interpret.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/idoerg/authorator"&gt;This Python package for managing large authors lists in LaTeX files&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; hope I never have to use something like this!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://pgbovine.net/research-group-dynamics.htm"&gt;This blog post on research group dynamics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A study at Google found five key dynamics that make for successful teams within the company: psychological safety, dependability, structure &amp;amp; clarity, meaning of work, and impact of work.
These findings can be adapted to improving research group dynamics in academia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="publishing"></category><category term="software"></category><category term="academics"></category><category term="jupyter"></category></entry><entry><title>New year reading roundup</title><link href="https://standage.github.io/reading-roundup-2016-01-02.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-01-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><author><name>Daniel S. Standage</name></author><id>tag:standage.github.io,2016-01-02:reading-roundup-2016-01-02.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://sasconfidential.com/2016/01/02/academic-scattering/"&gt;This eye-opening post about relationships in academics...&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...and the disproportionate pressure on women who hope to have children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I doubt any selection committee would admit on-record to thinking a family-free candidate is “perfect”.
Nonetheless, the traditional academic career structure is built around an assumption of mobility that is hard to maintain with any kind of relationships or dependents.
I’m still trying to figure out if I can manage to keep a pet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=10822376"&gt;This thread on Hacker News about video-based MOOCs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've participated in two MOOCs, but didn't complete either.
I have mixed feelings about the use of video to present the material.
In some cases, I could easily do without it.
But in other cases I think it was helpful.
Also, the types of autodidacts (many/most with a strong technical background already) that thrive in MOOCs may not need/want video as much as the average learner that would really benefit the most from a free or low-cost course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of 2016, I realised that video based courses in Coursera and Udemy are not ideal and are a drain on efficiency.
You cannot skim through content in videos and you are constantly wondering what you will miss if you forward the video.
You will have to adjust to lecturer's speed rather than choose your own speed.
You cannot listen to videos in noisy environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/m/pubmed/26711672/"&gt;This study on whether mom's kisses really do make owies feel better&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BACKGROUND: The practice of maternal kissing of minor injuries of childhood (boo-boos), though widely endorsed and practised, has never been demonstrated to be of benefit to children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OBJECTIVE: To determine the efficacy, if any, of maternal kissing of boo-boos in toddlers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.theguardian.com/environment/2016/jan/01/poachers-using-science-papers-to-target-newly-discovered-species"&gt;This piece from The Guardian about one case in which data sharing can be harmful&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But earlier this year, an announcement in the &lt;a href="http://www.mapress.com/zootaxa/"&gt;Zootaxa&lt;/a&gt; academic journal that two new species of large gecko &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3980.1.4"&gt;had been found in southern China&lt;/a&gt; contained a strange omission: the species’ whereabouts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Due to the popularity of this genus as novelty pets, and recurring cases of scientific descriptions driving herpetofauna to near-extinction by commercial collectors, we do not disclose the collecting localities of these restricted-range species in this publication,” the paper said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://ecoevoevoeco.blogspot.ca/2016/01/resolution-i-will-get-faculty-position.html"&gt;This blog post on getting a faculty position&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I know what you are thinking – “Yuk, I don’t want a job at the University of Southwestern Northern Nunavut.”
Neither do I, but here is the important thing to remember: &lt;strong&gt;You are not marrying your institution – you are dating it&lt;/strong&gt;.
If you don’t like it, you can leave – at any time and for any reason.
The key is to get yourself into a job where you can prove your abilities as an independent researcher, get your start-up money, get a grant, do some teaching, and so on.
That can happen at nearly any university in nearly any state or country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/351/6268/14.full"&gt;This (paywalled?!?!) article about the NHGRI possibly terminating funding for several model organism databases&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NHGRI Director Eric Green says that nothing has been decided and that rumors that his institute plans to phase out all of its funding are incorrect.
But he and other NIH leaders are searching for ways to make the databases more efficient, and are urging databases to consider charging for use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK131777/"&gt;This latest BLAST+ release note from NCBI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the upgrade from version 2.2.x to 2.3.x they have added provisional support for SAM output format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://biorxiv.org/content/early/2015/12/28/035493"&gt;This pre-print on amplification bias in RNA-seq&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Need to read!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computationally, read duplicates are defined via their mapping position, which does not distinguish PCR from natural duplicates that are bound to occur for highly transcribed RNAs.
Hence, it is unclear how to treat duplicate reads and how important it is to reduce PCR amplification experimentally.
Here, we generate and analyse RNA-Seq datasets that were prepared with three different protocols (Smart-Seq, TruSeq and UMI-seq).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://donmelton.com/2015/12/21/what-the-new-video-compression-strategy-from-netflix-means-for-apple-and-amazon/"&gt;This blog post on Netflix's new video compression strategy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tl;dr of it all is simply that Netflix plans on scaling bitrates up and down based on the complexity of their video.
So, slightly higher bitrates for busy action blockbusters and possibly lower bitrates for relatively static, flat cartoons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically what we’ve all been doing for years with variable bitrate (VBR) encoding.
But they’re trying to control that variance a lot more than an encoder like x264 typically allows.
In fact, as near as I can tell, Netflix still plans on encoding everything with a constant bitrate (CBR), but they want to be really particular about the target number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do that, Netflix will transcode every one of their videos a bazillion times at different resolutions and at different bitrates, finally selecting the smallest one for a particular title that doesn’t suck visually.
Seriously, their algorithm for all of this is quite clever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/tesseract-ocr/tesseract"&gt;This open-source OCR engine on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Found over Christmas break while chatting to family about OCR.
By the way, it's available in &lt;a href="http://brew.sh/"&gt;Homebrew&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="academics"></category><category term="work-life balance"></category><category term="moocs"></category><category term="funding"></category><category term="rnaseq"></category><category term="ocr"></category></entry><entry><title>Reading roundup</title><link href="https://standage.github.io/reading-roundup-2015-12-18.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-12-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><author><name>Daniel S. Standage</name></author><id>tag:standage.github.io,2015-12-18:reading-roundup-2015-12-18.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/articles/srep18087"&gt;This paper about a single nucleotide exon in &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we report that the &lt;em&gt;Anaphase Promoting Complex subunit 11 (APC11)&lt;/em&gt; gene in &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/em&gt; carries a constitutive single-nucleotide exon.
&lt;em&gt;In vivo&lt;/em&gt; transcription and translation assays performed using &lt;em&gt;APC11-Green Fluorescence Protein (GFP)&lt;/em&gt; fusion constructs revealed that intron splicing surrounding the single-nucleotide exon is effective in both &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt; and rice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://phdops.kblin.org/software-dev-intellectual-contribution.html"&gt;This (older) post about academic software...&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...which spurred some of &lt;a href="https://standage.github.io/misconceptions-about-research-software.html"&gt;my own writing&lt;/a&gt; this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would argue that the analogy with wet lab work would be that &lt;strong&gt;designing experiments&lt;/strong&gt; is like &lt;strong&gt;designing software&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;conducting experiments&lt;/strong&gt; is like &lt;strong&gt;implementing software&lt;/strong&gt;.
Now if we follow the general agreement that designing experiments is a valuable intellectual input to the scientific endeavour, by analogy so should designing software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2015/12/the-moral-failure-of-computer-science/420012/"&gt;This interview about computer scientists needing to speaking out about cryptography&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Waddell&lt;/strong&gt;: In your paper, you compare the debate over nuclear science in the 1950s to the current debate over cryptography.
Nuclear weapons are one of the most obvious threats to humanity today—do you think surveillance presents a similar type of danger?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rogaway&lt;/strong&gt;: I do. It’s of a different nature, obviously.
The threat is more indirect and more subtle.
So with nuclear warfare, there was this visually compelling and frightening risk of going up in a mushroom cloud.
And with the transition to a state of total surveillance, what we have is just the slow forfeiture of democracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://jcoynester.wordpress.com/2015/12/13/why-i-dont-know-how-plos-will-respond-to-authors-refusal-to-release-data"&gt;This long read on whether PLOS will enforce their data sharing policy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;King’s College London doesn’t want to release data to James Coyne from a study of chronic fatigue syndrome.
See if the absurd reasons make your blood boil as much as ours:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The university considers that there is a lack of value or serious purpose to your request.
The university also considers that there is improper motive behind the request.
The university considers that this request has caused and could further cause harassment and distress to staff.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.evocellnet.com/2015/12/replace-journals-with-recommendation.html"&gt;These thoughts about how recommendation engines might improve or replace journals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to replace the current system, by something less frustrating, would be to use automated recommendation engines.
I have tried Google Scholar recommendations and Pubchase and both work really well.
If we want to get rid of journals we need to figure out a way for such automated systems to mimic the journal's transfer of knowledge within and across communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="debugging"></category><category term="reproducibility"></category><category term="academics"></category><category term="shell"></category></entry><entry><title>Reading roundup</title><link href="https://standage.github.io/reading-roundup.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-12-11T00:00:00-05:00</published><author><name>Daniel S. Standage</name></author><id>tag:standage.github.io,2015-12-11:reading-roundup.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0128026"&gt;This PLoS ONE paper about stable identifiers for genome projects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When working on an ongoing genome sequencing and assembly project, it is rather inconvenient when gene identifiers change from one build of the assembly to the next.
The gene labelling system described here, UniqTag, addresses this common challenge.
UniqTag assigns a unique identifier to each gene that is a representative &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;-mer, a string of length &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;, selected from the sequence of that gene.
Unlike serial numbers, these identifiers are stable between different assemblies and annotations of the same data without requiring that previous annotations be lifted over by sequence alignment.
We assign UniqTag identifiers to ten builds of the Ensembl human genome spanning eight years to demonstrate this stability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manuscript completely reproducible (automated) using &lt;a href="https://github.com/sjackman/uniqtag-paper"&gt;this repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://rik.smith-unna.com/command_line_bootcamp"&gt;This web app for learning the shell in your browser!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bootcamp tutorial text was adapted from &lt;a href="http://rescuedbycode.com/linux-bootcamp"&gt;the original&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="http://www.keithbradnam.com/"&gt;Keith Bradnam&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.datacarpentry.org/spreadsheet-ecology-lesson/02-common-mistakes.html"&gt;This checklist of common spreadsheat mistakes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Excel is an arguably horrible tool for data management, but it's a starting place for many scientists.
Great guidelines on how to make the spreadsheet a lot less of a frustrating experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://michaeltomasson.wordpress.com/2015/12/03/one-reason-you-didnt-get-that-grant-is-because-theranos"&gt;This quote on academic salesmanship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, I assumed that excellent work would transcend the need for clever marketing and charismatic presentation to sell it to the proper audience, but the longer I work in science, the more I see examples of necessary hard work labeled as incremental and dismissed and attention lavished on the well constructed story.
The veracity of which appears secondary, or is assumed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.genomebiology.com/2015/16/1/274"&gt;This from &lt;em&gt;Genome Biology&lt;/em&gt; on self-serving motivations for reproducible research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so, my fellow scientists: ask not what you can do for reproducibility; ask what reproducibility can do for you!
Here, I present five reasons why working reproducibly pays off in the long run and is in the self-interest of every ambitious, career-oriented scientist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.carlboettiger.info/2013/06/03/DOI-citable.html"&gt;This quote about DOIs and citability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what do we mean when we say a DOI makes something ‘citable?’
If this is shorthand for the properties we would want in something citable: persistent identifier, archival content, machine-readable metadata, than we should start to recognize other things that share these features.
Further innovation requires valuing the features the DOI provides, not simply a “brand name” researchers recognize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/darylginn/status/669457664276094976"&gt;This tweet on software debugging :-)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;The 5 stages of debugging:&amp;#10;&amp;#10;1. What?&amp;#10;2. Why?&amp;#10;3. How?&amp;#10;4. Impossible.&amp;#10;5. Oh.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; daryl (@darylginn) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/darylginn/status/669457664276094976"&gt;November 25, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</summary><category term="debugging"></category><category term="reproducibility"></category><category term="academics"></category><category term="shell"></category></entry></feed>