<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Daniel Standage</title><link href="https://standage.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://standage.github.io/feeds/roundup.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://standage.github.io/</id><updated>2015-12-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Reading roundup</title><link href="https://standage.github.io/reading-roundup-2015-12-18.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-12-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Daniel S. Standage</name></author><id>tag:standage.github.io,2015-12-18:reading-roundup-2015-12-18.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/articles/srep18087"&gt;This paper about a single nucleotide exon in &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we report that the &lt;em&gt;Anaphase Promoting Complex subunit 11 (APC11)&lt;/em&gt; gene in &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/em&gt; carries a constitutive single-nucleotide exon.
&lt;em&gt;In vivo&lt;/em&gt; transcription and translation assays performed using &lt;em&gt;APC11-Green Fluorescence Protein (GFP)&lt;/em&gt; fusion constructs revealed that intron splicing surrounding the single-nucleotide exon is effective in both &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis&lt;/em&gt; and rice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://phdops.kblin.org/software-dev-intellectual-contribution.html"&gt;This (older) post about academic software...&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...which spurred some of &lt;a href="https://standage.github.io/misconceptions-about-research-software.html"&gt;my own writing&lt;/a&gt; this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would argue that the analogy with wet lab work would be that &lt;strong&gt;designing experiments&lt;/strong&gt; is like &lt;strong&gt;designing software&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;conducting experiments&lt;/strong&gt; is like &lt;strong&gt;implementing software&lt;/strong&gt;.
Now if we follow the general agreement that designing experiments is a valuable intellectual input to the scientific endeavour, by analogy so should designing software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2015/12/the-moral-failure-of-computer-science/420012/"&gt;This interview about computer scientists needing to speaking out about cryptography&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Waddell&lt;/strong&gt;: In your paper, you compare the debate over nuclear science in the 1950s to the current debate over cryptography.
Nuclear weapons are one of the most obvious threats to humanity today—do you think surveillance presents a similar type of danger?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rogaway&lt;/strong&gt;: I do. It’s of a different nature, obviously.
The threat is more indirect and more subtle.
So with nuclear warfare, there was this visually compelling and frightening risk of going up in a mushroom cloud.
And with the transition to a state of total surveillance, what we have is just the slow forfeiture of democracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://jcoynester.wordpress.com/2015/12/13/why-i-dont-know-how-plos-will-respond-to-authors-refusal-to-release-data"&gt;This long read on whether PLOS will enforce their data sharing policy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;King’s College London doesn’t want to release data to James Coyne from a study of chronic fatigue syndrome.
See if the absurd reasons make your blood boil as much as ours:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The university considers that there is a lack of value or serious purpose to your request.
The university also considers that there is improper motive behind the request.
The university considers that this request has caused and could further cause harassment and distress to staff.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.evocellnet.com/2015/12/replace-journals-with-recommendation.html"&gt;These thoughts about how recommendation engines might improve or replace journals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to replace the current system, by something less frustrating, would be to use automated recommendation engines.
I have tried Google Scholar recommendations and Pubchase and both work really well.
If we want to get rid of journals we need to figure out a way for such automated systems to mimic the journal's transfer of knowledge within and across communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="debugging"></category><category term="reproducibility"></category><category term="academics"></category><category term="shell"></category></entry><entry><title>Reading roundup</title><link href="https://standage.github.io/reading-roundup.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-12-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Daniel S. Standage</name></author><id>tag:standage.github.io,2015-12-11:reading-roundup.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0128026"&gt;This PLoS ONE paper about stable identifiers for genome projects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When working on an ongoing genome sequencing and assembly project, it is rather inconvenient when gene identifiers change from one build of the assembly to the next.
The gene labelling system described here, UniqTag, addresses this common challenge.
UniqTag assigns a unique identifier to each gene that is a representative &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;-mer, a string of length &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;, selected from the sequence of that gene.
Unlike serial numbers, these identifiers are stable between different assemblies and annotations of the same data without requiring that previous annotations be lifted over by sequence alignment.
We assign UniqTag identifiers to ten builds of the Ensembl human genome spanning eight years to demonstrate this stability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manuscript completely reproducible (automated) using &lt;a href="https://github.com/sjackman/uniqtag-paper"&gt;this repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://rik.smith-unna.com/command_line_bootcamp"&gt;This web app for learning the shell in your browser!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bootcamp tutorial text was adapted from &lt;a href="http://rescuedbycode.com/linux-bootcamp"&gt;the original&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="http://www.keithbradnam.com/"&gt;Keith Bradnam&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.datacarpentry.org/spreadsheet-ecology-lesson/02-common-mistakes.html"&gt;This checklist of common spreadsheat mistakes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Excel is an arguably horrible tool for data management, but it's a starting place for many scientists.
Great guidelines on how to make the spreadsheet a lot less of a frustrating experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://michaeltomasson.wordpress.com/2015/12/03/one-reason-you-didnt-get-that-grant-is-because-theranos"&gt;This quote on academic salesmanship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, I assumed that excellent work would transcend the need for clever marketing and charismatic presentation to sell it to the proper audience, but the longer I work in science, the more I see examples of necessary hard work labeled as incremental and dismissed and attention lavished on the well constructed story.
The veracity of which appears secondary, or is assumed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.genomebiology.com/2015/16/1/274"&gt;This from &lt;em&gt;Genome Biology&lt;/em&gt; on self-serving motivations for reproducible research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so, my fellow scientists: ask not what you can do for reproducibility; ask what reproducibility can do for you!
Here, I present five reasons why working reproducibly pays off in the long run and is in the self-interest of every ambitious, career-oriented scientist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.carlboettiger.info/2013/06/03/DOI-citable.html"&gt;This quote about DOIs and citability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what do we mean when we say a DOI makes something ‘citable?’
If this is shorthand for the properties we would want in something citable: persistent identifier, archival content, machine-readable metadata, than we should start to recognize other things that share these features.
Further innovation requires valuing the features the DOI provides, not simply a “brand name” researchers recognize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/darylginn/status/669457664276094976"&gt;This tweet on software debugging :-)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;The 5 stages of debugging:&amp;#10;&amp;#10;1. What?&amp;#10;2. Why?&amp;#10;3. How?&amp;#10;4. Impossible.&amp;#10;5. Oh.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; daryl (@darylginn) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/darylginn/status/669457664276094976"&gt;November 25, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</summary><category term="debugging"></category><category term="reproducibility"></category><category term="academics"></category><category term="shell"></category></entry></feed>